[nearby infant crying]
[yawning]
[door opens]
[footsteps approach]
[rattling]
[tense music playing
in background]
[baby fussing]
[scalpel tings]
[dramatic music plays]
[man narrating]
Circumcision is the most
common surgery in America.
Whether or not you choose
to learn about it,
it's there,
directly impacting
the majority of American men
in the most intimate
way possible.
[Georganne Chapin]
One of the things I found
about this issue is that
nobody who thinks about it
will ever forget it.
They might not ever want
talk about it,
they might spend time
explaining that it's not
an important issue,
but people will circle back.
[narrator]
And yet, many Americans
have never taken the time
to think deeply
about circumcision.
Circumcision is the surgical
removal of the foreskin,
the foremost part
of the male penis.
And in America, it is typically
performed on infants
within the first
few days of life.
No other
industrialized country
routinely practices nonreligious
infant circumcision
other than America.
Isn't it odd that
Americans have never had
a national conversation
about one of the central
practices of their culture,
a practice which affects so many
on such a personal level?
[people chattering]
One group is
starting a conversation
about circumcision in America.
Intactivism is a social movement
of people who believe
that all children
have a right
to keep the genitals
they were born with.
Cutting any part
of their genitals off
is a violation of human rights.
And there are activists
all over the world
that understand our message,
that boys and girls
are born with a body
that is their right to keep.
They feel that that boy's right
to decide for himself
is more important
than the parents' right
to decide what's best for him.
It's a very powerful,
compelling topic.
For one thing, if
you've acquiesced to having
your child circumcised,
and then you hear later
that it might not have
been the right thing,
that's a mortifying feeling.
It's a feeling either that
overwhelms you with--
with embarrassment
or grief or rage,
or it's one that
you wanna dismiss,
but it's not a neutral thing.
It's never
a neutral thing
for a parent.
The five most sensitive
parts of the penis
-are removed
during surgery.
-Wow.
I'll read up on that.
I didn't know.
I just thought
it was an incision.
I had no idea they
actually removed tissue.
It's very harmful,
because it's done to the baby
without their permission.
[man] You guys know
that it's hygienic,right?
-You do know that, right?
-It's not.
-It's not?
-[man 2] I mean, you think
we just came here
and set up a demonstration
without knowing what--
You know--
you know it is hygienic.
You know, women have
foreskin as well, right?
They have a little foreskin in--
-That's totally different.
-Why?
That's totally different. Why?
because they have
sensitive nerve endings,
-and it's--
-And you don't?
[Georgeanne]
If you're a circumcised man,
it's a potentially awful
thing to think about.
"Okay, I was tied down
when I was a baby
"and somebody cut
part of my body off.
"That's not so great,
"but I don't remember it.
Maybe-- oh, you know
what? I'm fine."
All of this stuff
comes into play,
and I don't think
you can just walk away
from feelings like that.
I've been around
a lot of social movements,
but the one's that unique about
the Genital Integrity Movement
is that it's all tragedy
through and through.
Something-- something
horrible happened to all of 'em
to bring 'em here.
Nobody-- nobody came here
feeling good about circumcision
and then got involved.
It's because something's
happened to them
or something's happened
to somebody that they
care about...
that's ruined their life.
and I don't think that's
too strong of a phrase either.
Circumcision fundamentally
changes you forever.
I went through what's called
the obsessive epiphany.
Everybody knows--
who's worked in this business
knows the epiphany.
It's the moment when you go
over the top on this issue,
and you realize that there's
more here than meets the eye,
and that even though it's
normative in your culture,
there's something
strange about it.
So I started doing
the late-night research, which--
virtually anybody
that you interview on
the subject will tell you
about the late-night research.
You just-- it becomes, it--
it takes over your life.
You're reading everything,
and you're reading the footnotes
to the footnotes
to the footnotes,
and going deeper and deeper,
and getting more and more
and more horrified
and more and more angry.
I mean, I can't even
remember what I did,
but I'm sure I put
"circumcision" in the
Google window,
if Google even existed then,
and just went from there.
And there's just massive
literature on the subject.
A massive literature.
You could spend a lifetime
reading it all,
whether-- whether from
a religious perspective,
anthropological, sociological,
legal, medical, bioethical.
Name your field or discipline,
and it has something
on the subject, so, I mean,
for the serious scholar, there's
just endless opportunities
there to horrify yourself,
amaze yourself,
and wonder why this
ever got started.
I went to my first
Intactivist gathering,
They were some of the most
interesting people I'd ever met.
[Dean Edell]
We were having my fourth child
in the hospital.
That night, we came
across Marilyn Milos,
who was a nurse in the hospital.
I discovered that there
were activists out there
in particular, Marilyn Milos.
Marilyn Milos, who we considered
the mother of us all,
who started sounding the call
30-odd years ago.
I went back to school to be
certified as a nurse midwife.
My last rotation,
May of 1979,
I witnessed a circumcision,
and that's when
I realized the horror
of what we do to babies
behind closed doors,
and I'd never heard a scream
like that come out
of the mouth
of a human being before.
I started to cry, and I was
standing next to the baby
to comfort him.
And the doctor saw me.
I just couldn't control myself,
and I have projectile tears.
And he looked at me and said,
"There's no medical reason
for doing this."
So not only was
I witnessing a torture
and mutilation of a baby,
I was also hearing that
it wasn't necessary.
And then of course the question
is, "Why then are we doing it?"
As I began to inform parents,
as I became informed
and informed the other nurses,
the head nurse came
to me one day, and she said,
"There's somebody on the floor
who's upsetting patients
by talking about circumcision."
And I said, "Well, we're all
doing the education.
Our jobs as nurses
is to educate."
And they said, "Well,
we can't have you upsetting
the patients, Marilyn."
So in 1985 when I was
fired, that's when we became
a nonprofit organization.
We filed a lawsuit in 1982.
A little boy was circumcised,
the mother didn't want it,
the father did.
We went to the Superior Court,
and the judge then said,
"Because circumcision is
"the oldest surgery
known to man,
"and because of the court's
reluctance to interfere
with family life,
"we're going to just say
that it's okay for the--
this is a decision
that's up to the parents."
So nobody was ready to hear it,
but I think that that is
how this sort of began
burgeoning forth
into the media and so forth,
and the backlash
with the Schoens
and the AAP.
I got interested in
circumcision in 1987
when I was asked by American
Academy of Pediatrics
to chair the American
Task Force on Circumcision.
The reason why they
formed that task force
was because the American
Academy of Pediatrics
actually put its foot
in its mouth in 1971.
Somebody wrote
a single sentence--
we don't even know
who wrote it--
saying there are
no valid medical indications
for newborn circumcision.
The American Academy
of Pediatrics came out firmly
against circumcision
and said that it was
unnecessary and there
was no reason for it.
And there was
a howl of complaint
from their membership,
from having performed this
surgery for so long and suddenly
turning their back on it.
But that became
the official policy
in the American
Academy of Pediatrics,
no valid indication,
and the anti-circs still
go back to that
all the time.
So they have a vested interest
in maintaining the procedure
and not angering
the 70 million American men
who are circumcised
and admitting nothing.
It completely was out
of line, but what the function
of the committee was,
to show that there
are indications.
So, that was that,
until my committee.
[Marilyn] And he went in
with the same laundry
list of excuses.
I know he finagled his way
into that position.
One of the things i said
before I took the job.
I says, "I don't
want this committee
to be under the thumb
of a committee
of the fetus and newborn,
which put out the other one."
And another doctor who was
on that committee at one point
threw his hands up in the air
and said, "I'm outta here.
"This is-- this is undemocratic.
You came in,
expecting to railroad
a position through."
We had one neonatologist
on the committee who was very...
committed to the old position.
And as a matter of fact,
before we even had
our first meeting,
he said, "I ain't gonna
change my mind."
Evidence has just been
accumulating in favor,
and every month,
you look at it,
there was another article.
I can't keep up with it.
There's one guy who keeps
sending me new papers.
Brian, stop sending me
another HPV paper.
So what I'm going
to tell you today
is that male circumcision
is better
for genital health,
public health,
and individual well-being.
The reason I became
passionate about it
is because I'm passionate
about science
and evidenced-based medicine,
And I became aware
that there are...
individuals in society
who are anti-science
and in favor of, you know...
retaining the foreskins.
There's a whole list
of risk factors
in life that people
should become aware of:
They're not to smoke,
not to drink to excess,
and another one is to insure
that their infant children
get circumcised.
I've had communications with
the chair of the AAP committee,
so I have been involved
over the years as
an international expert.
I am a person
who likes to speak up.
It might be my Baptist
upbringing. Who knows?
I'm not gonna preach religion,
but I've got this message
about health.
And I'd be happy to preach it
in all its various
shapes and forms,
and one of those aspects
is circumcision.
Those who oppose
circumcisions are
causing needless deaths,
needless suffering of people
in our community.
They should desist.
[man]: Do you really think
there's deaths that are caused--
-Absolutely.
-[man] Wow.
Deaths from HIV AIDS,
deaths from penile cancer,
and many deaths
from cervical cancer.
All preventable by circumcision.
In the parental decision-making,
there's beyond the medical--
there's the non-medical aspects,
whether you want to call
that cultural, religious,
aesthetic, family tradition,
personal experiences--
whatever it is,
people may use the medical
as a justification,
but it really comes down
to the end of the day,
Do parents really want it,
or parents don't want it.
I think that the report tried
to make an effort to bring
that out into the open
and say that not only
is that the case,
but that that's valid
and that parents' wishes,
even for their
non-medical considerations
are a valid part
of their making this decision.
In my practice,
I like to sort of define it
as... a tribal custom,
and if you belong
to a tribe that does it,
then you really want it.
And you can define "tribe"
however you want.
Now keep in mind, this is not
a universally accepted standard.
This is roundly condemned
by the Intactivists
who feel that
the overriding ethical concern
is the right
to bodily integrity,
and no one should be
able to alter your body
without your consent.
To me... that's actually
the more interesting
controversy, or reason--
topic for discussion
And we have to
decide as a society
"What are our
ethical standards?"
If we go back far enough,
what we find is that fathers
were circumcising their children
not ritually
in the Jewish style,
but as a sacrifice
to whatever deities they were
sacrificing to at the time.
As a matter of fact,
some scholars have given us
pretty good evidence
that circumcision may have
evolved as a substitute
for child sacrifice.
"How did it become a Jewish
ritual" is the question.
There you have to look
at the "Bible," the "Torah,"
the "Five Books of Moses,"
in which the creator
of the universe appears
to a 99-year-old man
named Abraham,
tells him that he will
be able to impregnate
his elderly 90-year-old wife
and that their
children will give rise
to a tremendous nation.
"However," he says,
"you must cut the flesh
of your foreskin."
What happened at first was
a fairly simple removal
of the front part
of the foreskin
and no more.
It was only later that
that practice evolved further,
first because Jewish men
during the Hellenistic period
wanted to perform
an athletic contest naked,
and they didn't want
to seem to be circumcised,
so they pulled
the remaining
foreskin back--
what's now called restoration--
they pulled the remaining
foreskin back and clipped it,
actually, in front.
so as to have
a normal-looking penis again.
In order to stop them
from doing that,
The Rabbis then instituted
a second phase
they called periah,
which meant removing
the rest of the foreskin
and removing at a much more
radical procedure.
It's important
to understand that,
because the kind of circumcision
that is performed
in Jewish ritual is
essentially identical to what
is done in the United States.
This very radical
and very destructive
kind of circumcision
in which practically all
of the foreskin is removed.
Circumcision became the major
symbol of difference
for Christians,
between Judaism
and Christianity.
This dates back
to Paul's letters--
"Galatians,"
"Corinthians,"
and others--
he says specifically
there that circumcision
does not matter.
It was so amazing to me
when I worked in a hospital,
and my first question would be,
"I see-- I see that you're gonna
have the baby circumcised,
and may I ask why you've chosen
circumcision for your baby?"
and they would say,
"Oh, because I'm a Christian."
And I said, "Do you know
that there's 120 references
"to circumcision
in the New Testament,
"that circumcision
is of no value?
"If you're a Christian,
you don't live by outward signs.
"you live by faith
expressed through love.
"Christ shed the last--
was the last to shed the blood.
"He was the ultimate
blood sacrifice for everybody.
We don't need to do this again."
"Oh, I didn't know that."
People are not just Christians,
they are Americans,
and circumcision is
an American procedure.
They're practicing
something because they
consider they're this,
without ever really
understanding what that means.
The next question
that we come to is,
"How in the world
did this get to become
an American custom?"
In Victorian England
in the late 19th century,
there was already
well-embedded belief
that masturbation
was a particularly
dangerous business.
That loss of semen would
weaken a child permanently,
might give him
all kinds of sickness.
They said, "We can stop
this very dangerous habit
by performing circumcision."
[Marilyn] We know that
circumcision began in England
to prevent masturbation.
Masturbation was seen
as this horrible thing
that could cause all kinds
of diseases and insanity.
And that just took
hold, you know?
We are a fairly prudish culture.
[Ronald]
And it sounds crazy to us today,
but in those days,
this was accepted.
[Geisheker]
Doctors in the 1860s
and 1870s claimed
that this would reduce
the child's sexual sensation.
But then in the 1960s, it
began to disappear as an idea.
Can you guess why?
Because the sexual revolution
made having sexual
pleasure permissible
for the first time, basically,
in American culture.
And so all of a sudden
the meme, the theme
that you were damaging
your child sexually
was no longer good advertising.
So it just simply went plink!
It just disappeared.
And now if
you talk to physicians,
they'll-- they'll claim utterly
that circumcision is
not sexually damaging,
that it's sexually neutral,
and that there's no harm in it.
And they forget entirely
the medical history they have
in their own occupation
that claimed exactly the
opposite for over 100 years.
Currently,
the benefit-to-risk ratio
of circumcision is 14:1.
That means there's 10 times
the risk you're gonna get
a urinary tract infection
as a baby,
that you'll have
a lower risk of HIV,
less human papillomavirus.
So when you add all those up,
there's 14 benefits,
some of them life-threatening.
These claims are irresponsible,
and it's a scare tactic.
I don't think there's a lot
of evidence for benefits,
and even if there
were some benefits,
this is a radical--
a radical solution.
Major claims
require major proof.
When you make a major claim,
and it is indeed a major claim,
that we doctors
can improve upon
the human body
by removing organs,
you've got to show
me major proof.
Medical justification for this
is a very interesting
subject in itself,
because it shifts
over the decades
from one topic to another.
Usually, it's the disease
that is most of interest
at the moment
that circumcision is claimed
to be, quotes, "good for."
It began of course
with cancer, the obvious.
Well, penile cancer
is a rare disease
of elderly men.
The likelihood any particular
man ever getting it in his
lifetime is very slim.
Those who do get it
tend to be elderly
and often have
very poor hygienic practices--
homeless men and so on.
Nonetheless,
the claim became popular
that if we circumcise infants,
we will be, quotes,
"protecting them
from this terrible disease."
Then in the '60s, they said--
now we've come
to the sexual revolution,
and they said, "Oh,
circumcision will prevent
sexually transmitted diseases."
Well, it didn't work.
It has never worked.
We have a high rate
of all of them in America,
as you know, where
most men are circumcised,
so that's ridiculous.
But just as soon
as one claim disappears,
the next one appears.
For a while, it was
urinary tract infections, UTI.
Well, girls get UTI's.
What do we do for them?
We give 'em antibiotics.
We don't chop off parts
of their bodies.
Once again, this is
an uncommon condition,
it occurs primarily in children
who have other defects.
It occurs in girls
more than in boys.
It is readily treatable
by antibiotics within
a day or two.
These are just the excuses,
and every excuse--
when one excuse is debunked,
the next one comes along.
It's almost like there's
a disease of the decade.
[Geisheker]
Name a decade and there was
some fear at work.
Guess what the latest
fear is these days.
HIV.
So, the only way
to figure out whether,
in this case, male circumcision
was gonna protect men,
was to do a randomized trial.
In this randomized trial
we identified HIV uninfected men
then we randomized
them to either get
circumcised immediately,
or delay circumcision
for two years,
and found that
the circumcised men
had 60% lower infection rates.
Those studies have really--
have really gotten legs.
I mean, they were picked up
in the popular press.
[Friedman] Those studies are
the reason why the American
Academy of Pediatrics
released their 2012
circumcision policy statement.
[Marilyn]
It's the circumcision
to prevent AIDS agenda,
with big, big bucks behind it.
If you're circumcised,
your chance of AIDS
is reduced by over 60%.
PEPFAR will provide $40 million
to support circumcisions
for almost a half a million
of boys and men!
All three of those studies
have been contested
for their statistical shortcuts.
So, here's the results.
The number of men who were--
who were circumcised
who got infected after 12 months
was one and a half
percent of the groups.
I've combined the stats to make
it easy, but the studies were
very similar.
The intact--
that is the men
who are not circumcised--
their infection rate was higher,
3.38% of the group.
So the absolute risk reduction
you could argue for
for circumcision is 1.8%.
And this is the stat you should
be reading in your newspaper,
not the 53%,
because that's
the relative risk reduction,
comparing the two little groups.
So, one of the commonest errors
in statistics is for people
to jack up their results
by talking about
relative changes
and not talking
about absolute changes.
With respect
to the other behaviors,
such as condom use,
men who consistently
use condoms
had lower rates of HIV,
The problem is with a...
behavior that requires
long-term lifelong adherence,
you don't get
the kind of... compliance
that would be ideal.
So we were very much looking
for other things that we could
add into the prevention mix.
So, here we've got
something that almost
works like a vaccine.
They've said circumcision is
like a highly effective vaccine.
Now, the measles vaccine,
you've probably had that.
99% of the people who get
the measles vaccine
and its boosters
become permanently
immune to measles.
That means you can have
somebody with measles
sneeze on you,
you know, cough on you,
do whatever
and you won't get measles.
That is what an effective
vaccine looks like.
Even if circumcision
has some effective protection,
it's not like a vaccine.
If you have sex many times,
you'll eventually get HIV.
It has already
been noted in a couple
of different African countries
that men are lining up
to get circumcisions so they
won't have to use condoms.
So, even if there's
a protective effect,
I believe that will be
completely swamped
by people not using condoms,
which are much more effective.
Well, certainly that was
a concern we all had.
It's what's known
as a "risk compensation"
in the jargon.
It means that if people
believe that they're protected
from a health risk,
they're going to increase
their risk behaviors.
But we followed men in the trial
and we've now
been following them
for four years after the trial,
and we see no evidence
that they increased their
risk behaviors.
Researchers attempted
to dispel this claim
and did a study,
showing that, "No, actually,
the men who were circumcised are
-more likely to use condoms."
-If anything, what we're finding
is that the men who choose not
to come for circumcision
have a higher risk profile.
They tend to be the cowboys who
don't take care of themselves
and then try to mitigate risk.
Well, if the men who
were circumcised are more
likely to use condoms--
go back to those
original three studies--
isn't that what's
preventing the HIV,
that they're more likely
to use condoms, maybe?
[Geisheker]
All right, let's go
through the flaws.
Flaw Five: Selection Bias.
Only men interested in male
circumcision were included,
and so that possibly-- that
automatically excludes others
who might've
been at lower risk
because of behavior.
Number six:
They were well-paid.
mostly were unemployed.
Frankly, the young men
were desperate,
and this way
they would get cash,
they'd get a free circumcision,
and they'd get
free health care
for a year or two.
which in the US would be
like giving you $12,000.
So that--
just the very structure
of these studies
makes them unethical in the US.
The next problem is that
for every participant infected,
a huge number were lost.
I mean, at the highest,
7.4 for every individual
that was involved was lost.
You have to wonder what
would've happened had those
people stayed in the study.
Small differentials
in the loss group could
negate these findings too.
And all of these flaws
are cumulative.
You know, the more flaws
you have in the study,
the more the results
of the study--
especially when they're small--
are called into question.
Flaw 13-- are you getting
saturated on flaws here?
Have I convinced you? [laughs]
It's worth noting
in relation to this,
continental Europeans have
never practiced circumcision
to any significant degree,
and yet their health statistics,
including their HIV statistics
are usually much
better than ours.
We have the highest
rates of HIV among any
industrialized country.
How can anybody sane
think that the country
with the highest circumcision
rate and the highest HIV rate
is gonna stop HIV
by circumcision? It's lunacy!
We predicted that
eventually after a few years,
they were gonna try
to translate these studies over
and make them applicable
in North America, and sure
enough, that's what they did.
I think it definitely has
implications in America,
so it really is a shame
that the rates of the procedure
have really declined
in newborns in this country.
To do something like that,
to advance your own career
on the backs of babies, that
is evil. I consider that evil.
They've gone from voluntary
circumcisions for men
to semi-voluntary circumcision
for young men
to involuntary circumcision
for infants, which is plan C
and was, I think,
the plan all along.
Leaving aside
the human rights issues,
there was a study that found,
to their surprise,
that female genital cutting
might possibly help in the
fight against HIV.
Well, surprisingly--
and I'm being sarcastic here--
surprisingly, no one is
proposing female circumcision
be done to stop HIV.
Well, no one should be proposing
that male circumcision be done
for that reason either.
Here are the contra-studies...
including three by the authors
of the African RCTs.
Studies, in other words,
that show that the effect is
not as good as you would hope.
So, I don't really
have any regard at all
for the HIV claims.
I find them distracting
and spurious
and... a waste of time.
People just think of the
foreskin as something that may
or may not become diseased,
and they think "Well, what
are the health benefits,
what are the risks
of this or that?"
They don't seem to factor in
the lifetime of pleasure.
I really love my foreskin,
like, I genuinely do.
This has nothing
to do with politics...
[laughs]
or Intactivism, really.
I genuinely love my foreskin.
I show people why that is.
-Okay!
-[crowd applauds]
So, I teach a seminar
where I actually instruct
intact men on how to have
orgasms with different areas
of their foreskins.
I'm a professional
foreskin demonstrator, folks.
I'm gonna show you
a couple of clips that
I use in my seminar.
The title of my show is
"The Revolution Will Not
Be Circumcised,"
where I basically
give people a tour
of the inner foreskin area
and show several different
orgasms that can be achieved
by... exclusively
stimulating these areas.
So, we're gonna start our trip
through the foreskin anatomy
with the frenulum.
Hands up, anyone who's never
heard of the frenulum before.
Well, we've got
a few of you. Exactly.
This is a really, really fun
part of the penis.
Some people call it
the male clitoris, because
many men can orgasm
from exclusively
stimulating the frenulum,
and I certainly can
just by licking the tip
of my finger
and just tickling--
just tickling very,
very, very lightly,
I can orgasm.
I have a video clip.
What I'm doing up here is
very, very lightly stimulating
my frenulum with my fingertip.
I'm not pushing hard at all.
It's just a very light--
very light touch,
just on this one spot
of my frenulum.
I really am getting
the orgasm exclusively
from this part of the penis.
There's no jerking of the shaft
or any-- or any touching
of the head of the penis--
these are the areas--
the traditional sort of ways
to achieve orgasm.
So factor those
out of the equation
and show people that there
are specific parts of the penis
that, in isolation, can give
you very powerful orgasms.
And in my case,
even multiple orgasms.
I'm a multiply-orgasmic male,
and I get my multiple orgasms
from parts of my penis
that I would not have
if I were circumcised.
I'm gonna show you a video
where I have five orgasms
with ejaculations in less
than two minutes.
just from touching this
one spot on my penis,
the ridged band.
You might've heard that men
don't have multiple orgasms,
Well, no, some of them do,
especially those that
haven't had a large part
of their penis cut off.
The pleasure potential of the
foreskin area is spectacular.
I can prove it...
in a way that
I think any reasonable
person can see.
A claim like that is
just in the imagination.
I'm sure he believes it,
but it's not supported
by any form of evidence.
I was one of four physicians
that performed a touch-sensitive
test on volunteer males.
[Marilyn]
We did a sensitivity study
that can determine
how responsive
certain body parts are
by using these monofilaments.
The monofilaments
are calibrated to bend
at a certain pressure,
so you know your results
are absolutely accurate,
and they're repeatable.
[Mark]
And we proved that the most
sensitive part of the male penis
was the foreskin, and in men
who had been circumcised,
the most sensitive
part was at the site
of the circumcision scar.
This was published in the
"British Journal of Urology."
The lead author's name
was Sorrells, Morris Sorrells.
The Sorrells study
showed a 75% loss
of fine-touch sensation
in a circumcised male
compared with the intact male.
And the findings
of our study showed
the most sensitive part
of the penis is ablated
with circumcision. Duh.
The foreskin, the frenulum,
and the frenular delta
are the most sensitive part
of the male penis.
Oh, there have been a lot
of studies on sensitivity,
that goes back
to Masters and Johnson,
way back in the '60s.
So, sensitivity--
the great major--
I don't know of any
studies that showed
any significant difference.
There are plenty
of studies that claim otherwise,
that claim that
men who are intact
and men who are circumcised
have the same sexual sensation,
but every one of those other
studies including the famous
one, Masters and Johnson,
tested only the glans,
the little fireman's hat
at the end
of the man's penis,
for its sensitivity.
And actually,
the glans has very little
in the way of sensitivity.
It was amazing to me
that these researchers
wouldn't understand that,
when the question
came up, "Why didn't
you test the foreskin?"
"Well, it wouldn't have
been fair, because the other
guys didn't have one."
Wait a second. If you're testing
sensitivity, isn't that what
you're trying to find out?
The minute you test
the foreskin with its 20,000
to 100,000 nerve endings,
you know that it's
gonna be more sensitive.
It's actually the foreskin
that is the male's main
erogenous zone,
and foreshortening it
or getting rid of it
definitely affects
the male's sexual sensation.
If you ask a man--
a circumcised man--
where the most sensitive
part of his penis is--
the absolutely most
exquisitely sensitive part--
it is where the frenulum--
or frenum, both names--
was attached.
The little vertical thing that
comes down from the opening.
Well, that's where
the foreskin was removed.
That's a hint for men
about what they've lost.
Now, the reason
why the frenulum
is capable of orgasm
is that it has thousands
and thousands of these nerves
called Meissner's corpuscles.
These are fine-touch nerves.
If you take your fingers
and run them over the back
of your hand...
You can feel it, but it's
not terribly pleasurable.
You can feel
the sense of touch.
However if you stroke
your palm of your hand,
it kind of tickles a little bit,
and it feels
a little bit better...
because there's
a high concentration
of Meissner's corpuscles there.
These are fine-touch nerves,
so what's interesting about them
is the lighter you touch them,
the more sensation
you get from them.
If you just run your fingers
firmly over your hand,
you won't feel much.
But if you go very lightly,
you'll actually feel
that tickle.
That's the Meissner's
corpuscles.
They're touch receptors,
which don't have anything
to do with sexual sensation.
They just touch.
If the foreskin is removed,
there's still plenty
of Meissner's corpuscles
in the rest of the penis.
It's not important.
But it's not just
about sensation.
The foreskin...
allows the penis to glide
in and out of itself
in a way that minimizes
friction, so it decreases
drying during intercourse,
and it decreases friction
for both the man
and his partner.
So, by removing
this part of the penis...
we have rendered
a structure that was meant
to have moving parts...
to being just a...
static structure.
[Marilyn]
For an intact male,
all those nerve endings
are stimulated as they
cross over the glans.
and then the foreskin is
everting, as with withdrawal,
the same thing happens.
For a circumcised male,
without having the foreskin,
he needs those long strokes.
An intact man just
needs small strokes.
He's stimulating himself,
he's being stimulated
by the female,
and the two work together.
The long strokes
take a man's body away
from the woman's body,
so she too is struggling.
When we have alter--
altered our genitals,
we have to alter the mechanics
of sex to compensate.
When you look at feminism
in the 20th century,
one of the big arguments
that feminists were making
was that women
were not enjoying sex
as much as they should,
because they are not educated
about their bodies.
They wouldn't know
about lots of the areas
that they can go for pleasure.
There's the clitoris,
the clit hood,
there's the frenulum,
there's the inner
and outer labia.
there's the pelvic floor,
the G-spot.
There's all sorts
of places women can
actually get orgasms from,
separate, you know, different...
sensations, different orgasms.
And the reality is
is that men are actually further
behind women in this regard.
Most men have no idea
of what the pleasure potential
of their genitals is.
They just think it's this
thing that goes in and out.
It's all very straightforward.
It's actually not true.
There's a lot more to it.
Here's another
way of looking at it.
This usually stops people.
I met an East African
doctor once who told me,
"If you circumcise women,
"they don't get
bladder infections,
they don't get STDs,
it's a lot cleaner."
You hear all the same
arguments all over again.
I liken this to female
circumcision, which everybody
feels clear about.
[Ryan]
We get very angry when we think
about female genital cutting,
and we want to use
very different words.
Removing the foreskin is
a public health measure,
which has multiple benefits,
and comparing...
female-- they shouldn't use
the term "female circumcision"
or male genital mutilation.
When my mother took me,
we we walking into this home,
this long and dark hallway,
it was the strangest
feeling I had.
It's like I felt chills
all over my body,
I felt cold...
and I-- I knew something bad
was going to happen.
And when I asked my mother
where she was taking me,
She said,
"I'm getting you a gift.
It's time to become a woman."
And then I saw
a young girl who was...
being taken out
of one of the rooms--
maybe she was seven,
I'm not sure--
who couldn't even cry
because her voice
was stuck inside,
And thus I knew--
I just knew that I'm going
to be one of those girls.
In Europe, I was like...
"Never happen to this,
all these women? No."
So, I started investigating
and realizing
that we have to speak
against it, so I felt like...
I have to use
my own private pain,
my own wound
to heal others.
Marilyn and I became friends,
and she said, "You should
come to my house."
So I came here to her house
and she showed me a video,
young boy who was having
the circumcision done.
She didn't say anything,
she just put that tape on.
[baby crying]
Same thing I saw myself,
the way they tied
the wrists and legs,
tiny, on his-- that table.
-And the cry...
-[crying]
I was like-- I was dead
already when I was walking
to that hallway,
laying down on that table.
That pain. I was--
it was me crying.
And then when I saw
what he was doing,
the doctor, how he was pushing
things up, cutting the foreskin,
I just couldn't-- I was--
I lost it. I just was like,
"This is-- this is mutilation."
How come in America,
we keep fighting about
the rights of girls,
and we're not saying
anything about this?
I don't like anyone
hurting a child,
so I'm against
both male and female--
I am a human rights
worker and activist,
that means
all rights of children.
I cannot select one side
and say, "I don't
hear your cry."
I ask people how do they know
that female genital cutting
is so awful
and male genital
cutting is so fine.
And they don't have any answer.
It's not like they've
actually gone and talked
to someone who had
experienced female
genital cutting.
They just, in their gut, feel
that female genital cutting
is terrible and male
genital cutting is fine.
And I propose that
that is due to our
socialization around gender,
that we actually think
male bodies are more expendable
and more harmable,
and female bodies are more
to be nurtured and protected.
And it has to do
with our imperialism
and our racism.
So we are very willing
to point fingers at people
of other ethnicities,
of other countries of origin,
and other cultural practices,
and not as willing to look
at ourselves really carefully.
It's okay to talk
about African culture,
barbarism, and mutilation,
but this is America.
We can't talk about,
you know...
hurting all the young boys.
For me, it's not an issue
of competitive suffering.
Everybody's hurt.
It's the first cut.
After that,
it just gets worse.
But it's the first cut--
of my cutting into your body--
that is the human
rights violation.
The torture for me is the same.
That first cut
is the same thing.
When they cut the child,
they cut forever.
Her mind, same thing
with the boys.
Where is
a human rights violation?
Do you have to cut off
this much of my finger
or this much
or is it my whole hand
that makes it a human
rights violation?
No, it's the first cut.
When ...
My freedom ends
where your body begins.
It's as simple as that.
Everything that America does--
even if some people hate it,
they will do what America does.
So I said if we pass laws
in this country
and say, "Hurting young girls
this way is an abuse,"
then the Africans
will think about,
"Oh my God, yeah.
I should stop this."
I went to every
politician I could.
I would speak everywhere,
and in '96 we passed it.
it took nine years.
Now the AAP got in a little
bit of trouble with this.
The American
Academy of Pediatrics...
actually said
because we do drastic
revisions on boys' genitals,
and that's considered okay,
then we should be able to do
a little piercing
of a girl's clitoris.
The AAP published
this paper that said
female genital cutting
was far less invasive
than male circumcision,
and that people from cultures
that cut their girls
would be tempted to go
back to their native countries
to have their girls
genitally cut,
so it would be better
if pediatricians could
just carry out a ritual nick
on little girls' genitals.
So it's a minor...
and it's not--
it's not gonna have any
long-term... harmful effects.
So they were
actually advocating...
that it's okay to do some...
messing with little
girls' genitals,
to take her to the doctor,
pull down her pants,
spread open her labia
and cut part of her clitoris,
or nick it, or do whatever.
I mean, no. That's disgusting.
The thought of it is disgusting,
and everybody ought
to be outraged--
well, everybody
ought to be outraged
about male circumcision--
but just the thought
that we could lose that
ground that we have,
that understanding about
what t means to have autonomy
over your own body
because we have
this horrible... situation
that everyone's ignoring,
and so in order to
have integrity,
you can just...
say it's okay to
do it to girls
or you have to say
it's not okay either way.
And so to see
that actual potential
manifest itself
was frightening.
[Georganne]
There's a federal law against
any cutting on girls' genitals,
so this new policy by the AAP
really suggested either that
doctors violate federal law
or the federal law be changed.
I mean, the thing
I had with the AAP
about having--
reversing a law
we passed in '96--
oh, I was mad like hell,
and I told them, I shamed them,
and they had to take it back.
It was a reasonable suggestion,
but the... academy--
American Academy of Pediatrics
then backtracked,
so we're back
to the way it used to be
of total disapproval
by the medical profession.
That really brought home
the detriment
of male circumcision
to me, because...
unless you draw the line
and have integrity
along that line,
it's-- it's not solid.
It's-- there's a danger
of people doing some
really horrible things
and using male circumcision
as a justification.
[Fuambai Sia Ahmadu]
If you're going to make
the argument
that female circumcision
is primarily conducted
on young girls
who are not able
to give consent,
well, what about boys?
They don't give consent.
My mother, aunt, and grandmother
approached me--
I was already in college--
and told me that they were going
to take us back to Sierra Leone.
But I didn't know anything
at the time about circumcision.
It was excruciating.
It was very, very,
very painful.
And for somebody like me,
you know, being mainly
brought up in the US,
this-- I just had
never experienced
anything like that.
This is why I say
that I do understand
some of the venom.
[laughs]
[mumbles]
Anti-FGM activists.
'Cause of course
I go back to that moment,
and I know how I felt.
After a couple of days,
the pain started to subside.
And then it was more
of the psychological,
"What have they done?"
[laughs] You know?
I had no idea
what I looked like.
"Am I going to have--
enjoy sex again?"
That was the test for me.
"Am I going to...
just even have the same desire?"
Of course, that didn't change.
And then, you know,
the same feeling,
the same "When my man
goes down on me"--
I mean, it just--
there was no difference,
so it didn't affect me at all.
I think for a lot
of women as well,
the external clitoris
is extremely--
I know in my case
it is extremely,
extremely sensitive,
almost too sensitive,
and that's how I was.
It was just too,
too, too sensitive.
I'd never had an orgasm
with oral sex prior to--
I have orgasms with oral sex.
Much of what I'm
saying is not a surprise
to researchers in the field,
because they're there,
they know, they talk to women.
Physicians-- the bulk
of evidence supports
my experience, but you
wouldn't know that from just
reading the activist literature.
because they say off the bat,
"Oh, this is something done
to diminish women's pleasure."
It's intended to be damaging.
It has to do with preventing
a girl from having--
having pleasurable sex
before marriage.
I was in Gambia for five years,
and a major emphasis
of my field work
was on sexuality.
I wanted to know,
"Am I unique?
Am I different?"
You know, when I tried
to explain it to them,
that, "Oh, western
women say that this is
the part that makes a"--
they just laugh.
I have all this data
that contradicts
what is being put out there,
and anti-FGM activists
are absolutely not interested
in data or evidence at all.
I realize it's
a very unpopular... position,
and I've certainly paid,
paid, paid, paid, paid my price.
I view myself as being
a kind of cultural ambassador
to explain this
particular practice
from the point of view
of supporters.
Most of the women
who engage in this,
who practice this think,
"There's nothing wrong
with what we do.
"This is-- it's been
handed down to us.
We're proud of it,
"We're honored by it.
We're better for it.
"We're cleaner.
We're more hygienic.
We-- we enjoy sex better."
This is what they say.
Why should we change?
It's like with the vast majority
of circumcised men.
try convincing them they're--
they've done harm,
or they're mutilated,
or, you know--
they wouldn't--
they would reject
that completely.
There have been a lot
of studies on circumcision.
Quite a few of them
have studied the pain.
Until the mid-'80s...
medical doctors
genuinely believed
that newborn infants
did not feel pain.
They were actually doing
abdominal surgery on infants
as old as 15 months
without anesthesia.
Then what happened was
some parents learned about this
and complained about it.
A woman on the East Coast
had a baby who had
open-heart surgery
without an anesthetic.
The mother got in touch
with Anand and Hickey,
and Anand then did this work.
The idea was
"Do babies feel pain,
and could they document
whether they did or not?"
Of course they did,
and it turned out that
the younger the baby,
the more exquisitely
the pain is felt.
When that result
was published in 1987,
it was concluded that yes,
newborn infants can feel pain.
I mean, what's
amazing about this--
again, the baby is crying.
but medical doctors
are not sensitive to
non-verbal responses to pain.
[Marilyn]
It took the American
Academy of Pediatrics years
for them to acknowledge
the pain in babies.
About 50% of boys
are being anesthetized.
That's-- that was
the latest figure I heard.
Previously, we thought
babies don't feel pain,
we don't have
to use local ane--
they scream,
but they scream
if they're wet,
if they're-- if they're hungry,
and so on like that,
and they get over it
very quickly, so, you know.
But now,
it's standard procedure.
The anesthesia is
not always effective,
and it doesn't eliminate
all the pain.
The topical is
the least effective,
and the ring block, when it
works, is the most effective,
but it take four injections
into the penis, which hurts.
The procedure is painless.
I mean, nowadays, if you
see somebody that's a real--
has done quite a few,
very often, the baby sleeps
through the procedure.
Well, sometimes infants
appear to be sleeping.
through a circumcision,
and that's an interpretation
of adults.
What's actually happening is
the baby is withdrawing
and a traumatic shock.
This is the only thing
they can do.
They can't escape physically,
so escape psychologically.
The idea that infants
don't remember pain
is another one
of those cultural myths.
Yes, the pain can be remembered.
The study by Taddio
many years ago,
who looked at the response
to immunization.
[Marilyn]
One group of these babies
being vaccinated
responded so dramatically
to pain, they said, "What
the heck is this about?"
And they went to see
what were the differences.
Were they breastfed
verses bottle fed?
Were they held more? No.
It was the boys who'd
been circumcised
that responded
hysterically to the vaccination
or responded much more
dramatically to the pain.
And the investigators
explained this by saying,
"This is a result
of neurological effects
from a circumcision
and a symptom
of post-traumatic
stress disorder.
When we were
taping the circumcision
at the hospital...
suddenly their light was
on that baby's penis,
and the nurse was scrubbing,
so the baby gets an erection.
That's the first thing that
happens, the baby gets a--
this is the baby's first
shared sexual experience.
Having been sexually
abused as a child,
the feeling in my stomach
was the same as it had been
as a sexually-abused child,
and I thought, "This is
sexual abuse."
That-- that was when I got it.
And then to hear the scream,
and I thought, "Oh my God,
not only is this child abuse
and sexual abuse,
it's violence."
So it's where sex and violence
meets for the first time,
and every sexual experience
is on that neuronal
background of pain.
By repressing those early,
powerful feelings,
we make it more
difficult to experience
and express any feeling,
because defenses
don't work that way.
They-- they work generally.
I view this not just
as a symptom
of circumcised man, but it's
also a cultural symptom,
because culturally,
we tend to avoid...
information about circumcision.
I asked a group of men,
"Please estimate the size
in square inches...
of an adult foreskin."
I got a range of responses
from one-half square inch...
up to maybe about six
or eight square inches.
The men who tended to minimize
the area of adult foreskin
tended to be the
ones who felt more okay
about being circumcised.
The actual area of the adult
foreskin may be 12 square inches
or even more.
If men don't recognize
the harm that's done to them,
they're likely to say,
"Hey, I'm okay."
There's also a psychological
motivation here,
and that is...
how men feel about
their sexual anatomy
is critical
to their self-esteem.
One of the main
reasons people are reluctant
to discuss it is that...
people don't want
to be seen as...
weak or damaged
but... that's what
circumcision does,
is it damages the penis.
It's an assault
on the sexuality of men.
And I struggled with it.
I struggled with it
for many years.
I went through
a period of denial.
I didn't wanna
accept that...
what happened to me
was significant.
I had to go through
a period of grieving.
I mean, it's-- it's a loss.
It's not just a loss of skin
or a part of the penis.
It's a loss of trust.
You grew up feeling like...
those who were there
to protect you, didn't,
to look out for your
best interests, didn't.
And it kind
of makes you question--
at least for me--
"Who can you trust?"
Distrust is a potential
post-traumatic stress
disorder symptom
among circumcised men
who are aware
of the harm
of their circumcision.
All of the men
who've talked to me
have told me--
well, almost all of them--
have told me that
they don't want to talk
to anyone else about it,
because they're afraid
of how harsh people's
reactions will be to them.
If you are willing
to accept a man's feelings
about circumcision,
then-- as valid, then you have
to question circumcision.
So, if you're not willing
to question circumcision,
then you have to trivialize
the feelings of the survivor.
I hear from men
who are extremely angry
about having been circumcised.
Feeling alone because
everyone else thinks its fine,
but they think it's not fine.
I hear from men
who feel a lot of grief.
Feeling like there's this--
this sexism that's hurt them
that no one notices.
Men ask, you know,
"Why was this forced on me?
And it's my body,
it should be my choice."
I've talked with a few men
who say they feel like
they have some kind flashback,
like, uh... phenomena
where they have
these dreams occasionally
that are violent dreams
where somebody's holding
them down and...
So some men have
a real lot of things that
they're working through,
and they're working
through them a lot more alone
than I wish they would be,
because-- because of society's
lack of concern for them.
We haven't talked at all
about foreskin restoration.
Restoring works by
tissue expansion methods.
[William Stowell] You end up
with a convincing-looking
replica foreskin
that does the job of protecting
the head of your penis
but doesn't actually have
any of the sensory
and neurological
benefits that a real
foreskin would have.
Since we started, there have
been a plethora of devices.
These are just... a hodgepodge
of different restoration devices
I've picked up along the way.
They all work in,
basically, the same way.
They all put extra tension on
the remnant foreskin you have,
and by putting gentle,
constant pressure on it,
you promote the growth
of new skin cells.
This should not be construed
as medical advice.
You should see
a qualified physician
before beginning any
foreskin-restoration program...
so they can laugh you
out of the office.
There's a guy who runs
a company, TLC Tugger,
who actually makes these,
and this is a very, very
quality device.
I finally decided, "You know
what? I'm 38 years old,
"What is going on
with my own penis?
"Why is it--
why does it seem to me
"like I'm getting
more and more numb?
I can't believe nature would
play such a cruel joke."
So then I went online,
and I learned that there
were men restoring,
but it sounded
really challenging.
But in 2001, I finally decided,
"I gotta pull the trigger.
I'm not gonna let this get
any worse. I'm gonna see if
this restoring can help me."
And I continued restoring
for four years.
May of 2003,
I finally had a way
of making my own device
that I felt I could make
'em for other people.
This is my workbench.
I keep different sizes
of molds that I've made.
There's just tons
of different sizes of those.
We have people that come in
every size that people come in.
So, to use our devices,
a circumcised man
will place the head of his penis
here in this recess...
and then he takes
the skin he's got left
rolls it up the shaft,
and forces it onto the outside
of this white Tugger body.
Then he puts the
clear retaining cone
over that skin
that's bunched up there,
and when you pull
on that handle,
instead of slipping loose,
it actually gets tighter
and so you can
add a strap tension
or you can hang a weight
and wear that
for 10, 12 hours a day,
whatever you wanna do.
Based on the number of men
that we help and a survey
that I conducted in 2010,
my best guess is maybe
a quarter-million men worldwide
are actively restoring.
A quarter of a million
restoring is a lot,
when you consider that...
there's a whole lot
of people who've never
even heard about it.
And there's plenty
of people who would never
even think to undo it.
The thing that's interesting
about this, it's very folkloric,
and from the bottom up.
This is something men
invented for themselves.
This is not something the
medical community invented,
and so everybody's
proud of their own method.
The one that I've been
using the most is this one
called the RecapEZ.
The best thing is
these all have the
funniest names available.
I'm entirely aware of that.
I even have a method.
My method's different
than other people's methods.
The easiest way to get started
with restoration is just--
we used to think it didn't work,
but it works quite well--
is manual tugging.
You know, you may just
grab ahold, pull the skin,
hold it for 10 seconds,
relax for 30.
Do it again.
Having helped so many men
and having restored myself
I have a sort of a formula for
how to restore successfully.
It's really about adding
tension to your skin
10, 12 hours a day,
wearing the retaining cone
every other minute,
and just letting the
calendar do the work.
There are no tricks.
There's nothing you
can rub on there.
No ointment.
It just takes time.
It really takes a commitment.
Not everybody's gonna
be able to do this.
To get there, guys might
need five, six years.
What is lost in circumcision
is-- is mainly about
80,000 to 100,000
Meissner corpuscles
that are
the pleasure center nerves.
What you get back is the feel
nerves in the glans.
When a penis
has been circumcised,
that is it lacks
the normal foreskin,
then the surface
of the glans is exposed.
It's open to the air,
which has a drying effect,
and its open to being
subject to friction
from clothing, from bedding,
and... the surface is constantly
rubbed and abraded.
As a result, the body has
a natural response
of accumulating
a thick, tough layer
so that the nerve endings aren't
constantly bombarded
with sensations.
That sometimes has been
called Keratinization
because if you analyze that
tissue under a microscope,
you might find keratine.
When a guy starts restoring,
one of the milestones
he's often looking for
is de-keratinization.
Within the first few weeks,
of-- of restoration,
men notice their glans is once
again glossy and mucosal.
That changes sex dramatically.
You get a more ticklish,
if you will, sensation
during intimacy,
and it just makes
you feel more alive
to really be experiencing and
feeling more of what's there.
Um, as time went on,
I did start to appreciate
that actually having slack skin
that could be manipulated
and slinked up and
down the shaft
during intimacy
was overwhelmingly
more important.
In sexual intercourse,
you thrust within
your own skin tube,
and this does away
with the need for any
kind of a lubricant.
It was an experience
I couldn't even describe.
I mean, I know the difference
between dry and dull
and delightfully ticklish,
but I never knew the difference
between friction only
and a slinking, gliding,
sumptuous massage,
which can happen when
there's all this slack skin.
The other thing I've--
I hear occasionally
is that guys are experiencing
what they call
a full-body orgasm
that isn't just...
a minute or less. I mean,
it goes on for a few minutes.
And... they're definitely
getting more out of it.
My main message
for circumcised men,
especially in America
where it's so prevalent,
is "If you only knew.
Foreskin feels really good."
You know, as I see it,
the big draw to becoming
a restorer is that it's
gonna improve your sex life.
But not everybody gets
into it for that reason.
It's not always, you know,
a positive, uplifting thing.
Sometimes it causes to surface
these-- these feelings
of reminding you
of your victimhood.
But for the most part,
you just-- you grieve that.
I have had,
during my tenure in NORM...
quite a number of men who
were just absolutely livid
about having been cut,
and they want
to kill doctors,
kill parents,
sue them, whatever.
And they are
very, very angry.
And of course, we try
and calm 'em down,
and tell 'em to,
probably, start restoring.
I realized...
that I'd been robbed.
You know? It's an invasion.
They stole something from me.
That was probably
my main motivation--
I took that anger, rechanneled
it into restoration.
Of the letters we get,
some of the more
memorable ones
were people who said...
"I-- I was unable to complete,
"if you will,
sex acts with my wife
"because I wasn't
feeling a thing.
"And so we couldn't
have children,
"'cause our sex wasn't putting
"my reproductive stuff in
with her reproductive stuff.
"But since I restored,
we now have a child,
and we're gonna
name him after you."
It's very satisfying to know
that somebody who was...
at some point in their life
must've felt they were
out of options
and that they just didn't get
to have the full measure
of human experience,
discovers us, and now they're--
they're back in the game.
The foreskin really is
not important for sex.
Men who have been
circumcised as adults
can tell the story best,
especially men
who were circumcised
for no medical reason.
I found out the hard way.
I got circumcised
at an older age.
I mean, it wasn't botched.
It was just
a regular circumcision.
It was like losing
your eyesight,
losing-- like being able to--
like eating food and not being
able to taste food anymore.
The doctor, he...
I called him up,
and told him
how upset I was that this is--
and he goes,
"It's usually
not like that.
You know, it's you."
And he goes, "I gotta go.
I have patients."
And he hung up on me.
So he was very
dismissive with me,
and then he sent--
[scoffs] it's funny.
He sent-- he sent something
in the mail saying
the whole thing was paid for.
Well, I didn't pay
for the whole thing,
so I think he was scared.
They'll say, "There's--
no other guys complain,"
but when the guys
do complain, they'll say,
"Oh, you're exaggerating,"
so this is-- this is
a no-win situation.
I got into a deep
depression and stuff,
but I realized that
I had to help myself,
'cause of lot of people...
want-- wants to minimize
the trauma, 'cause it is trauma.
Even I was scared
to talk about it at first,
'cause I-- you get
a very hostile reaction,
and I'm like... [scoffs]
"Oh you did that to yourself,"
or "Get over it."
It's like-- no, I'm speaking,
'cause I didn't
know better then.
And now I know.
I know that you can't take away
half the central nerve endings
from a penis
and still experience sex
the same way.
But if somebody says,
"I got cut for this
and that reason
and sex is better now
because I no longer have
this or that problem."
Good for them.
That's an adult choice
they can make,
and I'm tickled they were
in a position to make it,
and didn't have
it forced upon them.
I'm not against circumcision.
You know?
Not against it at all.
If you're a consenting adult,
you can do whatever you want.
But to take
a defenseless baby...
and strap it down, and...
sexually mutilate it,
I'm against.
I think for a lot of people,
they have a sense in their mind,
"This is what
a normal penis is."
The main reason
parents say that they
select a circumcision
for their child,
is because-- it's something
to do with appearance,
because they want their child
to look like their dad,
because they want
their child to look like
their children's peers,
or because they think
a circumcised penis
looks better.
All of those I really wish
would drive a chill down
our spines,
thinking like, "Is this
what we want to be
doing as parents?"
The idea that the parents...
have a right to mold
their children's appearance
such that it suits
them, I think is a
really frightening idea,
and I don't want our society
to move in that direction.
Your child may come back
to you 18 years later and say,
"Mom, Dad, you chose
to have a part of my body
removed that I want."
I knew I needed
to confront my parents.
It was something
that didn't seem right,
and it was something that
was already done to me.
Three days after I read
all this about it,
my mom was going
down to the living room.
and my lip was
kind of quivering.
I was really nervous,
'cause I was already
fairly upset abut this.
I'd said, "Well, I found out
what circumcision was."
And I said,
"Well, why was it done to me?"
And she'd kind
of talked in circles
about it was a cosmetic thing,
it was parental preference...
claimed that parents
own their children,
and-- I do remember this
word for word--
used the term,
"You are mine."
It was really frustrating
to hear that, obviously.
I think it's kind of frustrating
for anyone to be told
by someone else,
"Hey, I own you."
I just tried to say,
"But I don't like it,
and it's-- it was my body
that was affected."
And she didn't take
that well, either.
It ended up turning
into a screaming match
where she had gotten up
and just knocked over
a bunch of cups on the table
and kicked them in my direction.
And I was on the couch crying,
and I was trying to form words
to explain to her how upset
and how sad I was,
but she was feeling the exact
same way towards me.
This was the spark
that started the terrible
relationship we have now.
[Aubrey]
You know, you have a little boy,
he's circumcised,
but he's expected
to get what he wants
without hitting or without
hurting or manipulating
other people.
So there comes a time
when he's going to realize
that part of his body
was forcibly removed,
and he may have any number
of reactions to that reality,
but subconsciously,
the truth is
it's allowable for someone
who's bigger than you
to hold you down and do
what they want to your body,
'cause it fit their opinion
of what was okay to do.
And so you have a real
disconnect between the concept
of equality and the reality.
And I just don't think
that it's possible
for us to grow
with that poison
sitting there.
If we wanna be
a real free people like
we claim that we are,
we can't do that and have
that underlying lesson
taught at our
most vulnerable time.
As time goes by, it goes
from just the knowledge
that it's not something
for my kids
to moving into the activism.
Then the more you know
about things, the more
you want to stop them.
Are we cool?
[laughs] Sorry.
I think it's important
to come with the kids too.
I know there are people that
say, "The signs are graphic.
Kids shouldn't see that,"
but it's real, it happens,
and hiding it from them--
what's the point of that?
My son is not even four,
he knows it's wrong,
he knows that it hurts
the babies to do that.
He gets it.
[boy]
I think we don't--
don't cut baby's penises off,
yeah, because that's not nice.
[Emily]
"I think we don't cut penises
off, because that's not nice,"
and this is
the stuff that he says.
When we see the signs, "Mommy,
why is that baby crying?"
"Well, it's sad."
"Well, what's happening?"
And we explained
that doctors tie him down,
they cut off part of his penis,
and it hurts him a lot,
and he'll say to me,
"It's mean!
They shouldn't be
allowed to do that."
He gets it.
It hurts a woman to know
that the man you love
or a man you want to love,
or your father, or--
or your best friend growing up,
that someone hurt him
in the worst way they could,
and that nobody cared.
And there are a lot of nights
where I will sit up until
2:00 in the morning
reading, reading, reading,
and trying to get my mind
off of things, and...
I can't, I'm crying,
I'm crying for my brothers,
and I'm crying for my father,
and for all the boys that
nobody cares to save,
all the boys that, you know--
if somebody would've just said,
"Have you thought about this?"
or if a doctor wouldn't
have been a complete asshole
and convinced a mother that
she had to mutilate her son
'cause it's necessary
for whatever reason.
I don't know. I don't know
how you can know
this exists in the world
and not wanna stop it.
In all of my flaws
and all of my failings,
I know that at least
I didn't do that to them.
I can't imagine...
I don't know.
I can't imagine the regret
of knowing that you
did that to your son
and then learning
that it was wrong.
It's time for our culture
to stop being complacent
about circumcisions.
It's time to go out and be
part of that ethical correction.
So, thank you very much.
Well, we went into the doctor,
she did the circumcision,
and his penis
was fine before that.
I heard him scream,
which was horrible.
I tried to get in there,
but they had locked the door.
And...
Once she allowed me to go in,
she said that he had
a concealed penis.
Well, what I didn't know
until recently is that it was
a botched circumcision.
I had told her that
he looked normal before,
and she just said that...
basically, I didn't know
what I was talking about.
because she does this every day.
[man]
At what point
did you start to realize
that this was something
the doctor had done
rather than something
he was born with?
Yesterday.
I knew something
was wrong all along,
but I knew yesterday
when I was watching
the speakers.
During-- Marilyn, she was
showing these slides,
I saw my son's penis on there--
concealed penis--
and she said that
it was a botched circumcision.
What happens here is
either the doctor has
removed too much tissue
on the foreskin--
[Shannondoah]
And that's when I realized
what had happened.
And then... it was-- it was
a really hard day for me.
I-- I haven't had a day
that hard in a long time.
I...
I realize that I did
something to my son
I shouldn't have done.
Some-- some men
feel like it is...
is as bad as being raped.
How could I have
done that to my son?
What if he feels
that way one day?
I didn't have the right
to do that to him,
and I didn't know
until I went to the NOCIRC
conference yesterday.
Yes, some of these are
disturbing, but until we really
see what circumcision is
and it's impact upon humans--
while these things may
not happen very often,
if it's you,
it's significant.
There's not
a single state
in the US
that requires outpatient
circumcision reporting.
And no doctor's required
to report a botch,
and I talk to pediatricians
all the time who say, "I see
two, three botches a week,
but what can I do?"
[Gillian]
John, you're mentioning no--
no way to track what
goes on in the outpatient.
There's no way to track what
goes on in the inpatient either,
because nobody's
keeping statistics.
There is no nationalized system
for tracking adverse events
aftr circumcisions,
so we don't really know
how many babies die,
or need antibiotics
or blood transfusions.
We don't know.
[man]
Yeah, I was just gonna ask...
I'm gonna educate
myself more, and...
I'm going to...
be an Intactivist.
I'm gonna put
the information out there.
I'm gonna do what
I can to make sure
that other women and other men
don't do this to their children.
Hopefully, in educating
other people,
I can stop this from happening
to anyone else.
At least...
some people, you know?
I-- I-- I feel violated.
I also want to give a voice
to the ways that parents
are ethically violated
by circumcision.
[reading out loud]
If I would've known...
before that scream...
that it would've hurt him,
I wouldn't have done it,
but she told me he wasn't
going to feel anything.
She totally lied to me.
I've always been talking
to doctors about it.
But nobody ever told me that
it was something that happened
because of a botched
circumcision until yesterday.
I talked to Kathya,
and she's the first person
that told me that's not normal.
They gave me no information.
Yeah, yeah. I mean a lot of
the people that I approach,
that I start talking to
at like 20 weeks, they--
they don't even know that
that's like something
that's not necessary,
that's cosmetic, that there
are repercussions, anything.
[man]
Did Kathya know before
the conference yesterday?
Yes. Maybe that's why
she asked me to go.
[indistinct chatter]
Parents should
know that these...
accidents are
extremely common.
When I did a case
for a young man,
who had had too much
shaft skin removed
and too much
inner foreskin lining left,
which resulted in a repair
where there's sort of a bulge
in the middle of the penis--
it's rather unsightly.
His own doctor volunteered
to the defense a video
in which he said,
"This isn't malpractice.
I repair one of these a week."
Of course that does not follow.
Merely because
he repairs one a week
doesn't mean
it's not malpractice.
What it means is
there's a lot of malpractice.
The complication rate
of newborn circumcision
is about three-tenths
of one percent--
anywhere between
0.1 and 0.5--
anywhere between one in 200
and one in a thousand,
and they're almost all minor.
Of course, the American
Academy of Pediatrics
claims that the circumcision
complication rate is under 2%.
Well, let's think
about this for a second,
just as-- just as
non-medical people.
Who-- who determines where
the complications occur
and when they occur?
And the answer is the
hospital, right?
The kid gets circumcised
on Monday and maybe has
complications on Tuesday,
but if they send
him home Wednesday,
the hospital never hears
about the complications.
There are lots
of botched circumcisions
or-- the complaints
of adult men:
Why-- why do I have
skin bridges?
Why do I have hunks
and slices missing?
Why do I have a curvature?
Why do I have tight erections?
Painful erections?
Tearing at the scar site?
Unfortunately, for those of us
who have been circumcised,
we'll never know what our penis
was meant to look like.
The penis you have now
is a man-made penis.
Somebody cut into it,
and they arbitrarily decided
how much of your penis
they would take.
And so now, your penis looks
like... what they thought
it should look like...
which has varying results.
You know, a lot of the time,
there's that phenomenon some
people call "boner's arc,"
where their penis is bent
to one side or the other.
I would say,
nine times out of 10,
if you look, the scar tissue,
behind the head of your penis--
say if your penis is bent
to the left a little bit,
you'll notice that the scar
is wider on the left,
where they've taken
so much skin
that there's actually
enough tension there
that it causes
your penis to obtain
that bend over time.
Nobody has ever assembled
all the complications
of circumcision,
including the adult fallout--
especially adult fallout-- ever.
If you talked
to an honest pediatrician
about the number
of damaged boys
he sees in a month,
you'd be astonished.
We did 1,600
circumcision revisions.
Many times, the lowest person
on the totem pole was
asked to do it.
You've probably heard
the old expression,
"See one, do one, teach one,"
which is often used
in residency programs.
And sadly, that often happens.
These are some
of the instruments
that are used.
This is a Sheldon clamp.
This company has just been
put out of business...
because it's injured
too many babies.
This is a foreskin
in a Sheldon clamp.
This clamp has caused
the amputation
of the glans
or parts of the glans.
But imagine that...
[clears throat]
being clamped
onto a penis,
onto a foreskin.
It's here.
This is a Gomco clamp...
and it's thousands of pounds
of pressure is put on--
so this is the screw
that goes down
they bring the baby's
foreskin up through this,
and then they start
screwing it down,
and that tightens
this cla-- this,
so the foreskin
is being crushed there.
The rest of his penis
is down here.
But imagine that
on a baby's penis.
Does that look like
a piece of equipment that
should be on a baby's penis?
And here it is for an adult.
Let's go into the Mogen clamp.
Myself and John Juliano
of East Northport, New York,
obtained a million-dollar
judgment against Mogen
Circumcision Instruments.
It involved a ritual
circumcision by a Jewish mohel
and the mohel did not appreciate
that you can entrap
the glans penis in the jaws
of the Mogen clamp.
He did just that...
and when the child
continued to bleed...
an other doctor who
was present noticed it.
Mogen Circumcision Instruments,
whom we had sued,
did not answer the lawsuit,
and they never showed up
at any hearing.
Are there Mogen clamps
being used today
in hospitals throughout
the country? Absolutely.
And frankly, I believe
the design of the Mogen clamp
is extremely dangerous.
I want to address briefly
something called the Plastibell.
The doctor's asked
to tie off that extra skin
and then because it's tied off,
it supposedly loses
its blood supply
and sloughs away.
And if for any reason
that knot is not tied
perfectly tightly,
it's a source of infection.
The fact that a child
can die from this
means I don't think that thing
should be on the market.
I really think
that circumcisions
are in jeopardy if it's always
the youngest person
who happens to be
on the OB team.
We would like
every person bringing
their child into the office
to realize that it
is not... mandatory.
And of course many times
those families say, "We really
want to get it done."
and that allows me to talk
about, "Here's how I do it."
[baby crying]
-[women laugh]
-[baby cries]
[indistinct chatter]
[Boyd]
Yeah, you can fuss as much
as you want, buddy.
There are a couple points
in the procedure
where he's gonna
get kinda mad at me,
so don't tell him my name.
And he's gonna have
to get used to having
that touched anyways,
'cause... that's the way it is.
30 gauge needle.
And this is where he's
gonna start saying,
"That darn Dr. Winslow.
I don't like that guy."
[baby fussing]
[Boyd]
I mean, one
obstetrician told me,
"You don't really need
to do local anesthesia.
They just go into shock
right after you start
doing the procedure,"
as though that's a--
that's a good thing.
Another key
to local anesthesia:
We put that down,
we leave him alone
while it takes effect.
[Boyd]
That's how you do it.
Now here's a good clue
that we've done
a pretty good job
with our local anesthesia,
'cause he's not really--
I saw one toe elevate slightly.
-[baby fussing]
-[Boyd] Okay, so that's
where he felt me
-teasing it off the glans.
-[woman] Mm-hmm.
[Boyd]
And he's gotta
put up with that.
[baby fusses]
[Boyd]
So there's
the little frenulum,
and we'll let the clamp
take care of that.
If you had five elephants
all piggybacked
on top of each other
on top of one stiletto heel,
that's the amount of pressure
that it's putting on that skin.
And it stays on there
for five minutes
to achieve fusion
of those edges.
Do you want to save
the foreskin? You really don't?
Okay, so now, there's an art
to removing this clamp.
I'm teasing it off
this clamp in a way
-that doesn't rip it or tear it.
-[crying]
[Boyd]
We're gonna free him
from this waterboarding device.
Mom, pick up the--
the sweet stuff.
"I want my mama." See that?
Those who do mutilation
of young girls
say the same thing.
"Well, now we have
doctors doing it properly
and giving a local anesthetic,
so there's no more pain."
"So now I'm gonna say it's okay?
"More power to you.
Thank you so much.
We're doing this.
Go and keep mutilating girls."
No, this is wrong.
Who gives you the
right to say it?
So it's same thing
in America.
The problem is that
doctors don't know that--
anything about the structures,
functions, development
and care of the normal penis.
I get a hundred complaints
a year from parents
whose child--
whose intact child,
not circumcised--
whose intact boy
was forcibly retracted
at a doctor's visit.
And the doctors learned
in medical school
to retract the foreskin
to clean under it.
It always has to be
retractable. You have--
and they can't leave it alone.
Well, unfortunately, there's
a membrane that attaches
the foreskin to the glans
in infancy, which lasts
on the average, until age 10
and can last as long
as age 17, 18, and above.
And that membrane,
once torn, cannot grow back,
but yet I-- I have
a hundred cases a year
of-- of doctors who--
and nurses--
who forcible retract boys
because they tell parents,
"You have to clean in there."
I often had patients
sent in, who--
little boys who had
not been circumcised
and their pediatrician thought
that the first thing to do was
to separate the skin
and push that foreskin back.
And we don't
believe that at all.
The rule is:
Only clean what is seen.
You do not need
to clean children internally.
And I would say that
most children by the time
they've reached puberty have
a fully-retractable foreskin.
Those two structures
separate on their own
over a period of time.
That membrane is
completely normal.
It's like the female hymen.
It's part of the body.
It dissipates eventually,
but it's not a problem.
Everybody in my generation
who was intact
in the 1940s, '50s, '60s
was forcibly retracted.
Millions and millions
of American men
were forcibly
retracted as kids.
Some of them recovered from it,
some of them did not.
Some of them still have
sexual troubles they don't
realize are related
to what happened
to them in childhood.
I'll show you a picture.
This is a picture of a child
who was forcibly retracted
at a well-baby visit.
That's a condition
called paraphimosis,
and at its very worst,
the glans would begin
to autoamputate.
What's the excuse for this?
This-this is--
well, this is a child injured
at a well-baby visit.
Our physicians group estimates
that this happens a hundred
thousand times a year.
Considering all
of the foregoing,
what does the AAP
say about all this?
The AAP, referred to several
times as the American
Academy of Pediatrics,
they say, "In cases such
as the decision to perform
"a circumcision
in the neonatal period...
well, it should be the parents
who determine what's in the
best interests of the child."
[Georganne] The statement
that the American Academy
of Pediatrics came out with
in 2012 was extremely revealing,
because it was
a real piece of trash.
It was internally inconsistent,
so it said things like,
"The benefits
outweigh the risks,
"but we don't really
know what the risks are,
because the risks
haven't been measured."
Now right there you got
a big problem, right?
And they stated this over
and over. "The risks have not
been studied systematically."
They also said things like,
"Reports of deaths
"and complications
were not considered
for this article because
they were case studies."
Those are children who died.
There were, I believe,
only five citations
that were references
to ethical statements.
One of them was the
AAP's own statement
about how doctors shouldn't
operate on their children.
Of course, one of the
task force members had
circumcised his own son.
So, I get called out
on this all the time,
because in an early interview,
when asked, "Did I have
my own son circumcised?"
I responded, "I did it myself
as a religious ceremony."
I did it because of my faith,
and that's why I did it.
And I didn't do it because
I think everybody should do it.
I did it because,
for me, that's my tribe.
I don't really...
want to hear about...
innocents' rights of
some obscure disease,
you know, 'cause
that's not really how
I made my decision.
My decision was
the non-medical factors,
but at the same time,
I don't want to hear that
how I defined my tribe
colors how I counsel others.
So I don't,
because if you're not
a member of my tribe,
I want you to do
what's right for you.
If, clearly, the risks were--
significantly outweighed
the benefits,
we-- we would
fess up and say that.
I mean, the AAP has no agenda
to promote circumcision.
They just want to promote,
"What's the science?"
I also think that there's
some legal liabilities.
I mean, the American Academy
of Pediatrics aren't stupid.
William Stowell is suing
the hospital where he was
born and circumcised.
[Geisheker] Their attorneys
I am sure have told them to
keep the ball in the air,
and so they're never
gonna turn against it.
When I had gotten involved
in the movement,
a lot of the people
that were involved thought
that the best way
to affect social change
would be through a lawsuit.
I was turning 18. In many ways,
I was just in the right
place at the right time.
They said, "Wouldn't it be
great if some guy who is
"really, really bitter about
what had happened to him
could file a lawsuit about it?"
And it just seemed
no question in my mind
that I had to do it.
We decided to bring the case...
and in the process
of doing so...
we discovered that his mother
had not wanted to consent
to a circumcision,
although she had done so.
But when we looked
at his medical records,
we found out that she had
signed the consent form
early in the morning when she
was still under the influence
of Demerol and other drugs
after having delivered him
by cesarean section.
That's very simple.
If you're going to get
a consent from somebody
and you know they're drunk
or under the influences
of drugs-- drugs that
may limit their ability
to actually appreciate
what they're doing, the
consent's completely invalid.
A wrongful circumcision case,
of course, is not just
medical malpractice,
it is also battery.
I was suing on the--
on the idea that I didn't want
the procedure performed at all,
that it was my body,
that they didn't ask
me for consent
regardless of whether there
even was a consent form that
my parents had signed.
We were well on our way
to trial before they settled.
We sued the hospital,
and they settled with us.
And then the doctor
decided to settle with us.
It made me appreciate the power
that an individual has.
being an activist myself
has also made me
feel kind of sad
about the people that
are armchair warriors,
so to speak.
So many angry, disgruntled
people who never do
anything about it.
Up until this
point in history,
as of right now,
I'm the only man who's
ever sued his doctor.
I think his case was
unique in the fact
that his mother had
not wanted to consent.
It's more difficult when
you just want to assert,
"My parents weren't
able to consent."
Because that at the moment
is a bold proposition,
although I believe it is
a correct proposition,
the law generally follows
society, rather than society
following the law.
What may be correct
intellectually may not be
what a court holds.
I think that's the impediment
of every young man
suing at 18.
New at 11:00, supporters
of a circumcision ban
in San Francisco have
gathered enough signatures
to put that measure
on the ballot in November.
[reporter]
Lloyd Schofield is the man
behind the ballot measure.
[man] Before this initiative,
did you have any background
in politics or community
organizing?
No. No, I didn't.
People have tried
to prevent Jews
from practicing our religion.
Circumcision is a fundamental,
integral piece of our practice.
Our chief opponent
Abby Michelson Porth
of the Jewish Community
Relations Council
She had a lot of connections.
She had a lot of power
and money behind her.
I did have a couple of cordial
conversations with her.
We were talking about a baby boy
who died from his circumcision.
She said, "Oh, well,
he died of anesthesia."
I said, "Well, if he
hadn't been circumcised,
he wouldn't be given
the anesthesia, and he
would not have died."
So I said, "Don't you
believe babies should
be given anesthesia
when they go through this
very, very painful procedure?"
And she said,
"No, that's my religion."
I said, "I guess we don't have
anything else to talk about,"
and that was the last
I spoke with her.
What happened was
they took us to Superior Court
to have the ballot initiative
removed on a technicality.
I think that if this law
had a religious exemption,
it would not have roused
the sleeping lion of people--
even though they're a tiny
percentage of the population--
who are strongly opposed
to any sort of regulation
of their religious
beliefs or practices.
Many religious
Intactivists said,
"This isn't gonna
go through unless there's
a religious exception."
I said, "No, we can't do that.
It's too late anyway.
"And I would not have--
I would not have put
my name on it.
"That is antisemitic--
is to say Jewish children
do not deserve the same
protections as everybody else."
But now, one of the campaign
tactics that the backers
are using is generating outrage
in the Jewish community.
[reporter]
It's an Internet comic
called "Foreskin Man."
This did a lot of damage
to the anti-circumcision cause.
Critics say this comic strip
is blatantly antisemitic.
Abby Porth showed us
comparisons of "Foreskin Man"
and images the Nazis used.
I went on TV, I said,
"This is one person.
He's not a member
of our committee."
That was what our opposition
was looking for,
and they used it
very effectively.
We really wanted
to have a discussion,
and this gave
our opponents
the excuse
they needed to not
have any discussion.
Circumcision is still thought
of as a Jewish practice,
so there's always
that idea that if you're
opposed to circumcision,
what this really is
is a hidden form
of antisemitism.
Where it's really coming
from is that people care
about the welfare of babies
and people care
about the welfare
of Jewish babies.
There is criticism
of circumcision within
the Jewish community.
I'm an example of that,
and there are many
other examples of that.
My father was a rabbi, so I grew
up in the Jewish tradition.
This wasn't done
for my own good.
This was not my
religious choice to do.
I was circumcised
on the eighth day of life
in a ritual circumcision
[man] What sort
of feelings came up when you
were initially learning this?
Uh, rage. Absolute rage.
If Jews respond
to circumcision critics
with a charge that
they're being antisemitic...
this is a way of avoiding
the merits of the issue.
Well, this is an
ad hominem attack,
that means you attack the man
instead of the argument,
and that way you can
shift the discussion.
So I'm gonna steal
the argument and the debate
back from the people
that wanna talk
about antisemites,
and I wanna go back to babies
and why babies have rights.
The baby's religious
rights means that you
cannot cut his body,
because he too, actually,
is born with religious freedom.
Circumcising someone is
a violation of that person's
religious freedom,
that they may-- they may
grow up and decide
to not be Jewish,
but now that their
body's been marked,
it's too late for them.
And nowadays,
you have Jewish families
who are practicing brit shalom.
[Mark Reiss]
Brit shalom is nothing more
than a covenantal
naming ceremony
without circumcision,
although most think
in order to be Jewish,
you gotta be ircumcised.
Jewish identity is
purely matrilineal.
In other words, you don't have
to be circumcised to be Jewish.
There's definitely not one
thought on this within Judaism,
and... I certainly don't want
the Anti-Defamation League
speaking for me.
I felt that being Jewish,
it was really important that
I protest as a Jew.
A rabbi came up to me and told
me that I was doing the right
thing, fighting for change.
Any time that I am
at a circumcision
all the feelings that you're
confrontizing in this are there.
People know something's off,
and once you see it,
you can't go back.
-It is what it is.
-I can't go back, and for me,
it was added baggage
that this is so ingrained
in the culture that I came from.
[Irwin] Understand,
we're forcing people,
we're gonna legislate people
into very significant cultural,
psychological laws.
-Now-- now, not equal to it.
-I understand that and--
'Cause one is symbolic--
I get it-- and one is...
-Yeah.
-...feel-- so I'm not--
I'm trying to say it both--
I hope you're hearing it.
-I hear it. You're doing a
wonderful-- an amazing job.
-Yeah. Okay.
You know it's gonna-- social--
-[Levitt] Someone said to me--
Human rights are irrepressible.
[Levitt]
I had some interesting
conversations with him.
He's encouraged me
to speak from my heart
without hate,
so in some way,
he's sitting here with me
as I'm talking now,
'cause I can get really
angry about this subject.
[man]
So, what was the ruling?
Very unfortunate,
and it has been stricken
from the election cycle.
We were pulled off the ballot.
so people would not
get a chance to vote
on it or discuss it.
This is a long battle.
Marilyn Milos here has
devoted her life
to protecting infants from this,
and we are going
to carry forward with all
of the work she's done
and add to it and expand.
It permeates...
so much of our culture,
and we don't talk about it.
It's very painful
to... work on this issue
in that environment,
in an environment
where we joke
about the feelings of men
who are being vocal
about their displeasure.
And you'll hear someone say,
"Well, they're--
they're in the fringe.
They're-- the majority
of guys are fine with this."
So, those who speak out
get blasted...
and those who don't,
suffer in silence...
and potentially perpetrate
the same horrific act on
their own children.
So, the cycle continues.
[man] What would you say
to men who are angry that
they were circumcised?
-Yeah. What do I say?
What do I say to 'em?
-[man] I'm just curious.
I'd s-- I'd say, "Get a life!"
I'd say, "Come on. I mean,
"there's 120 million males
in this country
"that have been circumcised
and are perfectly fine.
Go find another reason
for your problems."
That's what I'd tell 'em.
Three of my sons
suffered mutil-- torture
and mutilation...
because some doctor lied to me.
If I stopped doing this work--
oh, I'm gonna cry--
if I-- if I stopped
doing this work--
I think about my babies
on that board, so...
How do you apologize
to children for doing this?
How could you possibly say
enough "I'm sorrys"?
You can't, so I do the work,
and-- and in that
is the healing.
I don't know. It's not healing.
I don't--
you don't get over this.
You don't get over it...
but you can make a difference.
[babbles, laughs]
I need to stop for
a second for this.
[Morris]
Marilyn Milos was interviewed
several years ago.
and she came across
as a weepy...
People who saw it--
I didn't-- I mean, I just
felt sorry for her.
She had boys,
she had them circumcised
and it was probably done
without anesthetic.
That's where
she's coming from, I guess--
all emotional. Not good.
[Marilyn] I didn't
start out as a crusader
or as an Intactivist.
I just started out thinking
I was gonna hold the light,
and everybody would be saying,
"Oh good, we don't have to."
I had no idea, the emotional
attachment people have, even
to something so sick.
Somebody said to me, "Why you?"
And I said, "Because I heard
the scream of the baby."
He said, "Do you know
how many millions of people
have heard that scream?"
I said, "Well, then the
question is, 'Why not them?'
[chuckles]
"Why did it take till me?
You know? Why didn't everybody
stand up and scream?"
[William]
Real social change isn't
doing something grandiose.
Real social change is going out
and changing people's minds.
I've seen my friends
ideas spread throughout
the population.
When I first got into it,
we were still a fringe movement,
and now it's everywhere.
And it all started out
with a handful of people
just going out there
and passionately speaking.
[Georganne]
This is a huge activist cause,
and we will win.
We are winning. This is
the human rights issue
of the 21st century,
the American human rights issue.
The way we treat our baby boys
is kind of the last stand here.
Our culture is shaped
by what we do to boys,
affected by it forever.
Ultimately, we'll look
back and we'll say,
"We used to do that?"
And I look forward to that day.
[classical score plays]